hey everyone Brandon here somewhat sick
uh to present to you my writing lecture
my first one on World building this is
sanderson's laws it's one of my favorite
lectures I hope that you enjoy it
welcome to science fiction fantasy class
yay I'm
back so you may notice a certain
ruggedness to my voice um I during my
trip to Hawaii managed to get sick um
yay yeah um and then that sickness
managed to um give me a an infection in
my sinuses that burst my
eardrum yeah uh never had that happen
before unique experience um I have been
on antibiotics now uh long enough for
that to no longer be an issue but I'm
going to keep my distance back here just
in case um so if I look a little redyed
and sound a little rugged uh that is why
so today oh also that ear doesn't hear
so well so I may have to ask you to
repeat questions we'll see this year
here's uh still here is uh just fine um
so uh today we're doing sanderson's laws
um so this is a fun lecture I always
enjoy giving this one uh not just
because I named these things after
myself um but uh I do think magic
systems have become one of my things as
I may have told you before um I did this
somewhat deliberately when I was
breaking in um to the business one of
the things I'd noticed in the books that
I really like to read was when they had
a pretty well-defined what we would call
hard magic system um I didn't coin that
phrase um but it definitely is something
that I've helped popularize the idea of
a hard magic um and I think both hard
and soft magic are perfectly viable
methods of Storytelling um they do
different things they're both Tools in
your toolbox uh but I noticed I was I
really enjoyed them and uh I liked uh
reading them and I liked writing them
so I started talking about magic systems
and kind of really digging into what a
lot of different authors had done and
experimenting during those early days
particularly before I got published with
different types of magic systems and
really trying to zero in on what I love
in a magic system and
um over time I develop these laws uh now
these are not laws that everyone needs
to follow they're not that kind of law
uh these are rules I made for
myself usually when I did something
wrong in a book and I'll share some of
those things I did wrong and I came up
with a rule of thumb to help myself to
avoid doing that um that said I do think
these are three very important
principles not just for World building
but for storytelling in general um for
you to kind of focus on and just to use
in helping you learn how to not just
create magism but in how to plot and how
to World build and how to do characters
this one is mostly a plotting one this
one is mostly a character one this one
is mostly a World building one and as
I've said I feel like stories are plot
setting character glued together with
conflict now let's go ahead and make the
um the the point that in a story World
building is usually the least important
of those
three which is odd to say when you're
here to hear me talk about science
fiction fantasy specifically right uh in
fact I am the magic system guy and here
I'm telling you magic systems are the
least important of the three now ideally
you'll do all three really well you want
to have really strong characters you
want to have really strong plots you
want to have excellent World
building but it behooves you to
recognize that a story with a strong
plot and strong characters but weak
World building is still usually a strong
story but a story that has really great
world building and even good of one or
the other but really weak in one of the
other tends to be a weak story and one
that has great world building and is
weak in the other two tends to just be
an encyclopedia entry you might as well
be writing a uh an RPG guide at that
point and so we want to make sure that
our world building is done in service to
story The this the there is a you know a
a rule Above This which is whatever you
enjoy whatever makes you write whatever
reason you're here um that's totally
valid uh but if you want to treat
writing as a career like we pretend
everyone in the room wants to do if you
want to be selling books then your world
building should be in service of the
other two rather than necessarily a good
unto
itself this is in maybe direct contrast
to Grandpa tolken which is why there has
to be kind of a a rule above this he
kind of wrote his books
to show off the cool philology um the
cool uh what yeah cool philology cool
poems cool mythology that he come up
with um and that's okay right then again
uh Grandpa tolken didn't have to try to
sell books in today's environment and
indeed he worked as a professor the
whole time uh because you know books as
a as a career particularly fantasy books
well writing Epic Fantasy for career
career didn't exist when Grandpa tolken
uh invented the job so um so just keep
in mind you can do it for whatever
reason you want but these days I
strongly recommend World building and
service of narrative and hopefully this
will help you uh and I'm going to go
through the laws and we'll do a a Q&A uh
on each one after each
one and I'll also talk hopefully about
some of my other kind of philosophies on
World building as we we go through this
so let's talk about rule number one uh
sanderson's first law um so sanderson's
first law arose because I was sitting on
a panel at worldcon worldcon is one of
the major science fiction fantasy
conventions out there um I had been
attending a number of years as just a
fan before I sold
something I finally did and I they um so
I am I went in and typed in you they
have this form you could fill in saying
hey do you want to be on paneling and I
said I just sold my first book to t tour
um I'd love to be on paneling and they
you know in the uh the form said what
are you good at talking about what will
you be interested in and I wrote magic
systems I'd already started thinking
this is my thing and lo and behold they
made the um they put the paneling
together and they put me on how do you
write magic systems the panel which I
thought was really excellent I'm to this
day grateful that they they did that I
think this was was Boston um world Con
in Boston early 2000s um and
so I got to this panel all
prepared ready to talk about magic
systems and they sat us all in a row as
happens and the person running the the
panel they asked the question like let's
just start with your Basics what what
are the basics of do designing a uh a
magic system and we'll just go down and
have every person on the panel uh talk
about their philosophy on this and just
start with the basics and they went to
me first and I thought
okay I got a home run here it's my first
panel the first question I've ever been
asked as a pro I'm going to just you
know I'm going to be really do something
that I'm sure everyone's going to agree
with and is not going to be um
controversial at all and I said well um
obviously to have a good magic system
you need to have
rules I thought non-controversial right
um this like ba basic stuff everyone
else on the panel looked to me and said
no if you have rules for your magic you
ruin
it um you ruin the storytelling and I'm
like suddenly I'm like I have no idea
what I'm doing now all these other Pros
I thought I where what's happening um
what's going on well uh we had a really
good discussion and turns out that I was
the only only one writing Epic Fantasy
on that panel and the others were
writing urban
fantasy urban fantasy being a genre that
is more focused has one foot in horror a
lot of the urban fantasy does um and a
lot of horror you don't want to show
necessarily what the monster is capable
of doing you don't want to give all the
rules because if you give all the rules
you put the Power in the hands of the
protagonists and in a lot of Horror
Stories the horror is about lacking
control the horror is I can't do
anything about this the rules of society
can't do anything about this um and
indeed the types of stories they were
telling didn't need to rely on the rules
of the magic they were writing soft
magic systems with good reason so what
is a hard magic system what is a soft
magic system let's talk about this for a
minute because it's easy to
mistake EX external Logic for internal
logic when it comes to Magic
systems when I say A Hard magic system
this is a magic system where the reader
understands the rules maybe not the
beginning but can learn the rules of the
magic and they are internally
consistent and the story revolves in
some way around the characters mastering
those rules using those rules to their
advantage um and um you know turning
Magic magic into kind of another branch
of science a soft magic system was a
magic system where the reader does not
know all the rules and they can't know
all the rules it is a magic system where
um a sense of wonder or horror
accompanies the the use of something
magical it's a magic system where um it
seems to have no internal
logic and you can't necessarily
anticipate what is going to happen um
with the magic now a lot fall in between
right uh this is a spectrum you can have
something in between indeed some of the
ways you can have something in between
is I would say as an example Harry
Potter is a hard magic system for a
given book in general but soft for the
whole series you never knew what the
series can do and indeed JK Rowling was
pretty bad at at um at taking the
consequences of something she invented
for one book and a it to another book um
this does create problems where she has
to like destroy all the time
Turners um to get people to stop
complaining about them but it also has
the advantage of adding a sense of
Whimsy and wonder to the Harry Potter
Universe you never know what crazy thing
is going to happen and that can be an
advantage to a
story let's make sure that you
understand that internal logic is
different from external logic
let me explain external logic is often
accompanying often accompanies a hard
magic system I do this a lot where you
use our realworld understanding of
science to try to lend
credibility to a magic system and or to
give it some sense of uh immediate what
we say in the business grock ability you
can understand it a little bit better
because um that's an old term term from
Highline yeah an old Highline term for
being able to understand something um
its rockability goes up if you can
anticipate a little bit of it acting
like you would expect it to in our real
world this is for instance um when X-Men
says oh there's a gene that causes the
mutation which gives people powers that
is an attempt to apply some external
logic
to a magic system okay that doesn't mean
that it is a harder magic system than
for instance Superman who gets his
powers from the Sun
why who cares as long as they're
consistent that's a hard magic system so
don't don't make this mistake don't look
at something and say oh because it's
completely Whimsical in what happens
it's a soft magic system no as long as
as you the reader can anticipate it if
the rules are set out for you and you
can anticipate what's happening it's a
hard magic system external logic can be
fun I use a lot of quantum physics I use
a lot of things like fundamental forces
I play with a whole bunch of these
things in my books but I would recommend
you separate that one is there to just
kind of help lend a veneer of
respectability so to speak and to have
some fun with the way that physics works
the other is there as a narrative tool
meaning the internal logic is a
narrative tool all right so as I started
to think about this and started to focus
on different magic systems um I I
realize that there are great examples of
soft magic and they're usually trying to
do something different uh one of the
quintessential examples of the
difference between these two is in Lord
of the
Rings the one ring is a generally hard
magic system we can list the rules right
here right what are the rules of the One
Ring you put it on you turn invisible
but it corrupts you and when you're
wearing the ring s and his minions can
see you it'll betray you too it doesn't
make you invisible it accentuates your
powers that you already have okay there
you are that is true but as presented to
the reader see you're using you're using
appendix information which is not in the
the the uh the stories and we usually
throw that out for narrative terms but
it is true for instance I'll get like
yeah but good job we know the actual
tolken scholar um it accentuates your
your your the the attributes you have so
Hobbits turn invisible because they are
small easy to to look over um but in
narrative terms for the story turns you
invisible but saaron can see you and if
it gets to saaron the world basically
ends right we have our narrative rules
for the uh for the One
Ring what can Gandalf do no speaking
tolken
nerd whatever he wants for the plot
whatever the plot needs Gandalf to do
Gandalf can do lots of sparkles yes lots
of sparkles in in the movies it has
always to do with like light in some way
oh the tolken nerd is just shaking her
head oh no if you read all the
supplemental material you'll start to
get some of this but for narrative turns
in the book Gandalf is a soft magic
system we and indeed the hobbits who are
generally the lens through which we see
the story don't know what Gandalf can do
it's kind of
mystical he's very powerful he might be
some like he's really old is he a god
what is he is he an angel like if in the
story like if you read the supplemental
material you know but if you read the
story what is Gandalf he's a friend and
he can do stuff um and these two magic
systems work very well to show the
advantages and disadvantages of both
hard and soft magic with the One Ring
froto can use it to escape problems and
to solve problems if he's willing to pay
the
cost with Gandalf he exists to indicate
that the hobbits are very small people
literally and metaphorically in a very
large world that they don't understand
and there are forces moving that are
completely Beyond them and their current
ability to
understand Gandalf adds a sense of
wonder and magic and mythology to the
world when he uses his powers it is
generally you can't understand the
ramifications or what he's
doing and the narrative purposes that
him using his powers um does is usually
to either complicate issues in some way
for instance he saves them from the bog
but then he's no longer there to keep
the fellowship together so the
fellowship shatters Gandalf saving them
from the balog is a bigger complication
um than it is a Salvation um this is the
real power of a soft magic system
particularly one that's like has you
understand a little bit about it but you
don't understand the full ramifications
for instance the famous story of the mon
monkey paw this is a kind of hybrid
magic system that's really leaning into
the soft side like you know you can make
a wish but you don't know the
consequences that gives you one foot in
hard magic but mostly in soft magic and
that not knowing the consequences that
soft side of the magic lends a great
deal of horror and mystery and even
wonder to the use of the monkeys paw to
the point that you are horrified as the
hard side happens which is you know you
get three uh three wishes and you see
the escalating danger um so sanderson's
first law sanderson's first law is a
plotting law the idea is that your
ability to solve problems in a
satisfying way with magic is directly
proportional to how well the reader
understands said magic one of the
biggest complaints that people make
about fantasy from the outside not uh
being part of our world not enjoying is
they're like I don't like fantasy
because anything can happen that removes
the stakes and the tension um in their
opinion well you've been in this class
we've already talked about this stakes
and tension are something any story can
fix with the snap of a finger if they
want to doesn't matter what kind of
story it is it doesn't even matter if
it's historical fiction uh you can
probably name um some tarantino-esque
stories that they just break break what
happened in the uh in history uh and say
either oh it was recorded wrong or you
know like you don't have to follow
history uh you as the author can do
whatever you want you have that power
your job is generally to solve problems
in a satisfying way but not
always sometimes you solve problems in a
way that leaves a lingering hint of
discomfort or dissatis isfaction I would
say Gandalf saving them from the bog and
dying is an excellent example of the
cure being worse than the disease
narratively I mean not actually because
if they've all died to the balog saon
wins but you know what I'm saying um and
so the idea
is you want to
control with proper
foreshadowing how you are solving
problems in your story this is why it's
a larger than just magic systms though
magic Syms offer a great example because
people point at us and say oh you can
just you know wave a wand and solve the
problems well no not if we want the
story to be satisfying and the Art of a
writer is to make it
satisfying uh another example though of
why you might not want to make it
satisfying um just so you understand uh
there I don't believe I've talked about
this yet this class if I have you know
throw something at me uh something soft
um
so you will often see oh Scar's like
don't throw anything at him I'll tackle
you
um you've often seen in Stories the
sequence where a character shows up out
of nowhere to save the protagonists from
a big problem that they're having right
um this happens all the time in
stories this sort of story this sort of
sequence is very different when it
happens in the first third of a story
than in the last third in the first
third you may want the characters to be
like oh yeah my friend you know George
he's just amazing with a bow uh if we
only we had George to help us and then
lo and behold they get trapped by
thieves and then a bunch of arrows come
out of nowhere and George saves them is
that a satisfying resolution no but the
purpose of that scene is to let us see
firsthand how great George is so that
George can join the crew and then be
later used in a more interesting way the
purpose that scene is not to have a
satisfying resolution it's to introduce
a character if you do this at the end of
a story you have a very different
reaction and in fact I'm going to use
the Lord of the Rings films as my
example of this going well and this
going
poorly um my favorite of The Lord of the
Rings films is the second right I
absolutely love the second film I love
Helms Deep and Helms Deep is a wonderful
example of how to use something like
sanderson's uh first law we don't know
what Gandalf can can do he is a soft
magic but you can set up a hard magic
structure for using Gandalf and Peter
Jackson does that what does he do in the
films day on the look for me on the
morning of the fifth day right they're
going to this terrible fight that they
can't possibly win Gandalf says look to
me on the morning of the fifth day um
and survive that long it's the plot
setup is if you can last five
days
therefore I will save you and we trust
the Gand can save him right like save
them um you know he's going to go find
bones he's going to bring him back and
uh you know it's it's not in the books
but it works really really really well
as a plot structure and that whole
sequence where Peter Jackson makes you
forget the gals had said that makes you
forget that it makes the characters feel
like there's no Hope they've forgotten
when the morning of the fifth day comes
and Gandalf Crest the rise and and and
there's bones with uh with his whole
team um then you're like oh yeah and
then you know you'll you'll have the
little voice over look for me on the
morning of the fifth day boom wonderful
plot cycle right it it's a setup and
payoff the setup is last 5 days you win
they last 5 days and Gandalf comes and
save them and it's beautiful it's my
favorite moment in all three films um
they then don't manage to do the same
setup with the ghosts and Aragorn um and
again this is some deviations from The
Source material uh in large part I agree
with Peter Jackson's decisions uh this
one just doesn't quite land right we are
not set up as an audience or as
characters to be like we need to last
until uh until the ghosts arrive um to
save us instead set up this is our last
stand we must defeat and Conquer
otherwise you know um Gondor will fall
they fight they fight they fight they
lose Aragorn shows up with
ghosts and saves them and you're left as
a reader or as a viewer just being like
why did we fight shouldn't we have just
run and let Aragorn show up with the
ghosts right like can we send those
ghosts to
midor yeah they say they have to be let
go but come on just one more ride guys
um and it ends up being kind of a a
weaker plot cycle um very you know uh
it's still there there it's it's a great
film Trilogy probably the best um but
that is one flaw and you can kind of see
why we are wanting the problems to be
solved in the way promised to us we
don't want a deox Machina we kind of get
one all right um so Sanders's first law
is to encourage you when you're building
a magic system to think about these
things if you're doing a soft magic
don't have the magic save the day in the
end instead you need to focus on
characters and what they can do and what
they they want to solve unless you want
a different kind of resolution you can
tell a different type of story War of
the Worlds
ends with simply the humankind has been
destroyed and would have lost except the
common cold uh coincidental um saves
them by killing all the all the Martians
um this is in many ways an unsettling
UNS satisfying
ending that's the point we are not the
apex predator we are not as powerful as
we thought um it's a warning that you
know um we could be destroyed and wiped
out um if you want to have a Sanderson
esque ending generally what I'm trying
to do is to seed pieces of the magic
system that the characters can use as
tools and usually I'll put one step into
soft and be like there's things we don't
understand yet which allow me then to
explore new parts of the Magic in later
stories um and then characters will put
together the pieces figure out how to
manipulate these things um and you end
up with stories that lean into science
fiction sort of plotting um using the
magic as a new brand of Science and
Sanders's first law is kind of the way
to do that questions yeah um kind of
already touching on it but
is can you have like a hard magic system
that can swing all the way back to soft
or soft goes to oh yeah yeah you like
you can start completely soft and then
as people find the rules they end up it
becomes a hard magic system and you can
go the other way we thought we had the
rules we don't have the rules everything
we thought is a lie uh those are harder
to do but if you build your story around
it uh you absolutely can the key to keep
in mind is what's the emotion that you
want to have specifically at the ending
or in the conflict resolutions of your
stories and how are you shooting for
that emotion and how is the magic
enhancing that emotion rather than kind
of getting in your way here and then
back there how can you seed enough
details about your magic system that
they understand it but it doesn't
completely give away what they're going
to do with it in the end how can you see
it enough that they the reader
understands it but doesn't give away
what you're doing at the end um couple
tips here number
one put in more clues than you think you
need and scale back if too many of your
beta readers are getting it my
experience is that re authors withhold
too much and don't seat enough as a
general rule um that's obviously not
going to apply to every author um but
keep that in mind the other thing is be
careful about info
dumps so um the grand skill of writing
science fiction fantasy as I've said I
believe before in this class um is to
convey information to readers in such a
way that they don't realize information
is being conveyed to them that they
never stop and say oh this is getting
boring um because you're going into
details on the magic there are lots of
ways to get these details across in ways
that will not be as feel as much like an
infodump one is uh to make sure other
things are going on in the scene right
it's not just info dumping you're
getting across character and things like
this breaking up the the lessons so it's
not just like all dumped you usually do
that by inventing early on scenes that
show off one little aspect of the magic
system show it off really well and then
you build upon that uh in mbor I believe
I've mentioned before I purposefully
don't show the magic system early on I
know it's got a lot of rules to it I
want to focus on uh the setting and the
characters before I get into the magic
and so at the beginning of Mporn ker
goes and brings down um like an entire
manor house full of guards uh he just
goes you know John Wick on the mall um
right and I just cut because I'm not
going to show all that magic yet I wait
until I've seated some scenes where we
see a little bit of what Vin can do and
then once we get into a training session
with kelse here which is really very
physical tactile we're out in the world
it's not an info dump we're doing things
we're experimenting where you know cause
and affecting and building kind of the
ma uh master and Apprentice relationship
all kind of dealing with Vin's issues
all at once and you get the training uh
scene that's on the wall uh where she's
learning about Newton's Laws um and
things like this as it applies to uh to
alamy I put it off to there and it
works in stormland archive I just
launched you straight into it um
and it's a steeper learning curve I make
sure it's an action scene where lots of
things are happening uh filtered through
the lens of hopefully a very interesting
character doing something very
interesting and I try to make sure I'm
never giving too much at once but the
whole thing is much more uh dense in uh
in rules and those are just two
different ways that I decided to do it
back here um how do you write a write a
system that you know is a hard magic
system that 100% has rules but the
characters never really reach the point
where they're hitting those character
yeah um excellent and this uh arguably
is what tolken actually did right um
that if you sat tolken down and said
what can Gandalf do he'd be like oh this
and this and this and this and it has to
do with this and this and this and this
um and so what you know is different
from how you use it narratively and
narratively I would recommend that you
know if you have a soft magic system
knowing all of that is actually still
pretty useful to you you don't have to
have it but knowing it can be very
useful watch for your conflict
resolution that's the thing if the
characters can't don't know the rules
ask yourself what little pieces can they
learn and can they make use of them and
if not then con uh conflict resolve in
different ways um and you can set these
up right um You can you can have you
know payoffs that don't relate to the
reader the characters manipulating the
magic system um it's kind of not
completely there but it's the idea that
came to me while I'm saying this if you
think about Wizard of Oz the
movie at the end the Cowardly Lion is
given a heart right like it's just a
symbol but it shows like and it it
really doesn't relate to the magic
system they don't know what the wizard
can do he probably can't do anything um
right but you still get a payoff because
the Cowardly Lion showed
courage completely unrelated to the
magic he showed courage and he gets uh
you know uh he gets a medal right isn't
that what he gets he you know he he yeah
I guess the Tin man wants a heart and
the lion wants courage so the Tin man
gets like a heart but anyway the lion
gets gets his his courage reward
um boy it's been a while when I was a
kid you watched that show like every
couple of weeks cuz there were three
channels right and you just turn on and
you're like oh it's Wizard of Oz again I
guess we'll watch that like you
basically you're basically watching
Wizard of Oz or die hard because they're
on 24 hours a day uh on different
channels but now I realize I haven't
seen Wizard of Oz in like 30 years so um
but you can look everyone gets their
reward at the end and it doesn't really
matter that the ruby slippers can
teleport or what the rules of the ruby
slippers teleporting are it's the fact
that Dorothy showed the gumption to go
do the thing she needed to do and that's
what the plot set up for her to do so
she can get a magical
reward with it still being a soft magic
system and still be satisfying because
she achieved what she needed to achieve
as an individual that's what I mean by
making sure that the ending is character
focused rather than magic system
resolution ution
focused um right over here yeah um I'm
ask without giv any spoilers for this
form yes appreciate that yeah would you
would you say that ending a story where
a character overcomes something using
powers they didn't know they had oh yeah
is that oh I'm glad you brought this up
yes so uh minor spoils for missp one I
said each of these rules came from me
learning something by doing it wrong um
you're bringing up at the end of
mistborn book one I violate sanderson's
first law a character discovers a power
they didn't know they had and they use
it to solve problems how did this happen
well number one I hadn't devised
sanderson's first law yet um I was just
trying to tell a great story and the
ending of Miss born one lacked impact my
uh editor said can you do something to
just heighten the power and the impact
of the ending and I said yeah I've got
this whole thing I'm planning for book
we'll just start seeding it right now
right um and you can see how the stuff
that happens is very relevant to book
two I pulled it for it I used it then
the book comes out and people are like
wow I really like that book it's a bit
of a deox mocky at the end isn't there
and I'm like oh yeah there is now CU I
didn't see or foreshadow that at all um
and it becomes really relevant to book
two that's when I started to be like I
did something wrong there what did I do
what's the difference how can I avoid
doing that
again um and you will find other places
where I do similar things uh in books
intentionally because I want a different
emotional reaction than oh wow it all
came together now I understand um you
want to be doing these things
deliberately rather than accidentally
and there I did it accidentally and I
think it was a mistake um I think it is
one of the one of the weaknesses of mbor
the first book um is that uh that I I
relied on that instead of finding a
better solution that really more relied
on characters and or I should have gone
back and seated this so excellent
question you're on the ball I'm glad you
noticed that all right I got to go to
the middle here I'll come back here if
we we've got time so go ahead and then
we'll come to you so I was just
wondering how feasible is it to be able
to have like that sort of ending like
the day but like not in a way that it's
something that nobody
knows what just happened it's like
hinted that like
it is written in rules you just don't
know why yet is that yeah can you have
an ending where it is written in the
rules you just don't know why yet yes
right you can do anything uh just make
sure your emotional payoffs are
something different for
example ending of the first book TW of
Twilight what happens in the end first
book of Twilight Bella gets knocked
unconscious and the main uh kind of
conflict gets resolved while she's
unconscious people still love this book
why because it doesn't matter if the
good vampires can beat the bad bad
vampires it's not what the book's about
book's about is can this romance work
right and the romance working still is
the main conflict uh some people are
like no uh we won't get into we won't
get into that but as a novel it's been
very successful and you could argue how
can you have a successful novel when
your main character is unconscious for
the main resolution well that's not the
main resolution that's just the end of
the the quote unquote small P plot or
you know uh evil vampires whatever um
and so if your your resolution is
something else and then you have this
big event you're like we don't
understand this something big just
happened um you're satisfied for this
reason but you're disturbed for this
other reason uh we need to now go and
investigate why this thing we
anticipated happening didn't happen or
where this thing happened that we didn't
anticipate because it has huge
ramification you'll see me doing that
all the time uh in books uh just make
sure you have you know it's what is your
promises and what are your payoffs and
are you balancing what's unsatisfying
and what's satisfying and you're making
sure what's unsatisfying is there for
another emotional
purpose um especially when part of the
plot is about characters learning uh new
things or like uh re uh reanalyzing
rules how do you you know lie about
rules in a satisfying way without having
readers just feel like not
yeah how do you lie about rules in a
satisfying way I recommend very early on
indicating um hanging a lantern on it in
some way saying okay this is how we
think it works but here's three
historical examples of something that
happened that don't seem to conform to
this and we don't know why and that does
scare us but we can learn this part and
do it that sort of thing is really handy
for you as a writer uh and there's lots
of different ways to do this for
instance you can have your character
learning and they're like teaching you
know blah blah blah and have them say
well what about this and the teacher's
like uh don't think about that we don't
know or that's beyond you right and then
they're like ah that sounds like it's
really important H don't worry about it
never comes up right those sorts of
things you'll see all the time in
fiction and that's kind of the purpose
okay back here so I get that rule one
applies to solving problems in a
satisfying way but what about creating
problems with magic that you may or may
not understand awesome good question so
um what about creating problems you may
not may may or may not understand I
think I quoted this once already but if
not um uh Bryce Moore uh writer friend
of mine uh he's a librarian up in Maine
he was in the graduate program with me
at BYU he coined a term that I still use
which is called deex
wrench which does not work at
all in the uh in the Original Latin
Latin D no Greek um what's now deos is
is Latin right yeah but it's applied to
Greek plays that's confusing we should
go back and time and tell them you
should write this in Greek
um right um but deox wrench does not
work at all um but the idea is that he
says readers will be they will they will
take a little bit of you messing with
things hand of the author to make things
harder on the the characters um but if
you it too much they'll start to see the
hand of the author in the same way that
they see the hand of the author solving
problems and readers do want the
complications to come from choices that
somebody has made for instance if you've
got a soft magic system you you know you
can do X but you do not know the the
consequences
why but they decide to do X anyway you
can make Y is bad as you want as long as
it's kind of force out of uh you know
how big these complications can be uh if
it's the middle of a story you treat it
differently than the end of a story um
but readers want decisions and
consequences not just and decisions can
be someone else you can have those
moments where the everything seems to be
going well and then something goes wrong
and you realize that flaw was there all
along and it was just waiting to explode
um you can have that the same way at the
end of 6 cents you have the moment of
realization where the uh the clues were
all there you can have the clues all be
there for something going wrong be
careful about deox wrench it is worth
thinking about the inverse of this is
also true making things more hard for no
reason on the characters Works to an
extent but readers will get tired of it
there are exceptions to this rule right
like there are entire stories built
around how awful things are for certain
characters and how things constantly go
wrong George Martin made an entire
career out of you know sometimes people
can take a take an arrow to the knee uh
and instead of retiring to a nice job in
Skyrim they just die um and you know uh
that's realistic um you know infection
happening because you took an arrow to
the knee readers will take that um to an
extent particularly if it's the right
type of you've given the right type of
tone promise now you had a a comment
here where does the name for this come
from which one de French de wrench yeah
not French uh sorry this is probably the
whole voice problem yeah the French are
always causing problems
uh no he called it Dex wrench yeah uh
glad you said that I'm not sure how uh
how articulate I am with uh with my
current ailment all right any questions
over here all right I'm going to go back
to the this person over here I told I
couldn't get back to yeah how would you
present a magic system you want to have
come across as hard but it's like really
complex and confusing and and based off
something most people wouldn't know
about um I would present it that way
meaning I would have a reader a
character start to get involved and then
you know um I would technobabble them to
the point where their characters like
all right I understand that you
understand it wizard person right this
is basically how St does all of its
magic system it's like you know parkcard
calls down and says Jordy I need you to
do X and Y and jordy's like all right me
and data will do you know a b c d and
then Picard's like okay I trust you tack
on something reflector dish something
solve it uh how long will it take three
days do it in two right
um we get the sense that Jordi and data
know all kinds of stuff we don't need to
know it cuz Bard doesn't need to know it
all Bard needs to know is that he has to
stall for two days uh and then if you
actually have all that stuff worked out
um which you know Star Trek sometimes
did um then you can use it to Great
advantage through to make your story
have internal logic and things like that
but you don't have to you don't have to
throw it all at the reader be careful
about using the cliches right like oh
man how many of you are tired of the in
English please um right phrase that
always gets shown you go to nerd nerd
talks for a second they say in English
please when the nerd didn't say anything
that confusing um maybe I'm speaking to
the to to a crowd that is self-
selecting into that not being confusing
but yeah all right we're going to do
these two questions then we're going to
be done okay so first here and then up
there how is this uh you know this first
rule apply in a story where one of the
main conflicts is kind of uh man versus
nature where magic is the nature right
yeah so uh how does it apply in person
versus nature where the magic is nature
um I would say it does apply very well
some of the strongest fantasy stories
out there uh dragon Riders of per um is
an excellent example um where like
because nature is the magic generally
these lean very well into hard magic
systems characters are figuring out how
the science of stopping nature works and
it's a kind of a scientific Race Against
Time to see can we figure this out can
we solve this problem um right and uh if
you haven't read dragons Riders of per
uh it is basically this sort of thing um
there are some person versus person
conflicts as well but the idea is like
we're all going to die because this
certain phenomenon is happening we have
a small number of dragons that can
protect against it but we need to find
out the extra Powers our dragons have
and learn to harness and manipulate them
rather than just uh going with you know
what we've always pretended to
understand before and we need to
understand the actual why this uh this
catastrophe is happening so yeah um my
question is about how can you foreshadow
things in a way that your reader
understands um but your character
doesn't look too stupid for not oh boy
what an excellent question how can you
force out things in a way that the
reader understands but the character
doesn't look too stupid uh
generally You' want the character to be
thinking the things that you want the
reader to be thinking okay so if the
reader is going to guess something you
generally want the character to guess it
unless they have unless they lack
information because you've seen from
other viewpoints which is one way to do
it or unless they lack information but
like because you have external logic
that they don't have but that's
dangerous even if they there's no reason
they should understand that you
understand you know germs and they don't
so you understand how this thing is
spreading and they don't the reader
going to have trouble because they get
it and the characters don't and that
barrier is going to be a problem so
generally Your solution is have the
characters figure out early on the
things that the reader going to guess
and have them try and have those fail
anyway so that there's a layer Beyond
and you do this by having um red
herrings um by having cause and effect
reversed um like u meaning re like the
minor spoilers well kind of more Major
Spoilers for elantris elant gets by
completely by everybody have M having
mixed up cause and effect they think the
cause caus an effect well really the
effect was the cause and they just have
the timeline slightly wrong and because
of that uh the conventional wisdom
doesn't work and the magic is broken and
when they figure out cause and effect
was
reversed then it comes together right um
and so things like that where you can
have the reader the character be
intelligent and it still not work out um
and then slowly get them the information
particularly if you're using a red
herring to distract the reader um uh
this works really really well uh getting
good at red herrings red herrings being
the the reader expects it to be this
because they've read a lot of books you
make that thing sound like it's going to
the case but not too obvious so the
reader like I've got this figured out
then the reader will stop trying to
guess because they have their Theory and
then near to where the climax is going
to happen the real is going to happen
you show them that they were wrong
because the readers characters think of
that and then it's not true and then the
reader's like wait this thing I've been
assuming all along that I knew who the
killer was isn't the case I'm Suddenly
at C and then they have the reader asked
to
scramble to try to figure out a new
Theory while the reader characters are
doing the same thing it works really
well so all right let's go on to
sanderson's Second Law um I touched on
this one already uh but I want to dig
into it a little
deeper and this is that flaws are more
interesting than Powers themselves I
spent this one came about uh because I
spent a long time trying to think of
really unique and interesting powers for
my Magics right um when M borne came out
I think I've told you the guys this
story before um but I'll I'll reiterate
because you know I'm the teacher and I
can do that um I thought about how cool
this like M the alaman the pushing and
pulling came from watching uh films like
Star Wars and reading books um where
people have telekinesis and thinking
about well where's the Leverage coming
from right did do Newton's laws apply um
when when Darth Maul points and then
points and something Zips across I'm
like wait a minute have I ever seen the
force do you just point and it zips
across the room and hits the wall where
what's going on here um and it works
just fine for Star Wars but I'm like
what if you built a telekinesis around
Vector physics and uh cause and effect
and things like this and I designed this
whole cool magic
and I thought wow this is so
original and then I released the book
and people love it they're like wow it's
so cool it's such a great magic uh and
someone comes through my line um early
on uh it couldn't have been too early
cuz no one read mbor one um but uh I
told you that story haven't I U Miss
born one kind of flopped a little bit
all right I'll go on tangent mode um
I'll finish my story then I'll go in
Tangent mode uh someone came through my
line and said wow I love I love Miss
born um it I magnino is my favorite
super
villain and you just did a wonderful job
of having Magneto powers and I
went I created Magneto just with more
steps um it's not that original he's
even my favorite super
villain I love Magneto and I just
created Magneto um
and I'm like what made it so interest
like why was it so much fun to write if
it was just copying somebody else and I
realized it was in the limitations the
the flaws uh and by flaws I mean uh
limitations and hindrances and uh costs
uh and flaws themselves um and I
realized what made it interesting was
because because you couldn't just move
anything anywhere which magnito kind of
can the characters had to position
themselves in in specific ways and they
had to account for the the uh the costs
um the limitations of the magic only
being able to push directly away from
you or pull directly towards you having
to take into account the various weights
uh and it sounds all very finically when
you explain it but in the story it makes
the characters have to be strategic in
their application of the of the magic
and it turned out to be a lot of fun to
write and it turned out to be a lot of
fun to
read so because of this um I realized
that flaws are more interesting than
Powers rather than racking my brain for
new and original Powers I found that if
I focused on new and original
limitations to a magic um that the
characters had to use in interesting
ways the magic just got way more
interesting um like kaladin can
basically just fly poorly right he he's
got the superpower of flight but
bad yet it's so much more interesting to
write than just a character can fly um
because he's having to make certain
decisions and apply certain skills to
being able to use his bad flight and
because of that the reader can
anticipate what it can do and what its
limitations are and it becomes way more
interesting to read because of that this
is a large scale rule that we're going
to get into in a second but I'm going to
tell you my tangent um so oh boy I gotta
be careful we'll run out of time um so
miss born one came out and elantas did
pretty well uh alant sold 10,000 copies
in hard cover um which is really solid
it's not um it's not you know breaking
down any doors uh bu breaking any
records I should say it's not uh it's
not you know no one's no one's breaking
down my door to get me to sign for more
books there's the mixed metaphor I was
looking for um but solid Publishers
encouraged they paid me $10,000 for it I
earned maybe 20 to 30,000 in royalties
that's what they like to see um right
they they got a good deal they didn't
overprint uh so M borne comes along
they're like we're going to print a
little extra on this right
um but I made the decision to not
publish um a sequel to launchess but do
a new book series and when you're a new
writer you have a little extra shine on
you and people pay attention
particularly back in the day the
bookstore days it's less so now when
they get Bri's new shelf and be like Oh
Brett first book by new author people
would buy it um Miss borne didn't uh it
sold like 8,000 copies then the
paperback of Miss borne came out a
really bad cover um love my color
illustrator he did wonderful work on on
the others but that paperback just
didn't land and then it just sank like a
stone and so that's the closest my uh
career came to just completely uh
completely dying um and it recovered
because I convinced them to put a new p
uh cover on uh misbourne to release a $5
Edition uh and we pushed really hard for
a package and that paperback took off
and sold really well to the point that
mistborn 2 see back in the day the
bookstores they would look and they say
well this first book sold 10,000 second
book sold 8,000 just to be sure we'll
order 6,000 of mbor 2 and that's what
they did but then it instantly sold out
and they had to reprint until it ended
up selling like 12 or 14 uh and so
that's when that's when my career that's
when things started to take off and then
mbor 3 became a bestseller so um so yeah
that's the close I've ever come to my
career completely flopping oh you don't
have to clap for me
um I got lucky um part of it was having
a really good Agent who was like uh yeah
this is probably the cover the book is
really solid people who are reading it
love it uh we need to get this book into
the right hands and we need to recover
this and then him going and fighting to
get a new cover on that and the $5
addition was my idea um Robert Jordan
had done that once uh with eye of the
world and so uh I guess it was his idea
uh yeah so don't applaud uh just
uh it's it's it's scary those are those
first few books sorry Rachel are scary
uh they are scary all right flaws versus
Powers uh this is this is a larger than
just um magic system thing as well I
said this is a character thing your
characters will generally be more
interesting in what they can't do or
won't let themselves do than in what
they can do uh super Superman is the
classic example of
this
Superman has like three different
stories that people tell about Superman
that are really good what are they
centered
around someone has
Kryptonite there's a monster stronger
than Superman holy cow or ah slow Lane's
not in love with me and my Powers most
of the time depending on who's writing
me don't let me have anything to do with
that I have to interact as a normal
human being and I don't know how to do
that with Lois Lane my Powers don't help
me um this is not a coincidence right
most of the most powerful stories told
hit characters where they're
weak Lord of the Rings Works in part
because it's not Aragorn or Gandalf who
have to carry the ring it's Frodo who
has to carry the ring right what happens
Gandalf has to go up against someone
stronger than Gandalf in Saron who's
been in anced you know through the
powers of evil um and who was always
Gandalf Superior and then the balog
who's like equally matched to him right
like Gandalf has to face uh challenges
bigger than him um Aragorn gimble and
leg Los they just got to fight armies
you know um and those are barely a
challenge to them by the way Lord of the
Rings meme of the week for those who
love it uh in the movies uh there's that
great standoff where Aragorn and
everybody's like drawing the forces of
Mordor you know and they've chopped the
head off the mouth of s for some reason
um um and you know they're there and
Aragorn yells for froo and starts
running I saw a meme that then cuts to
the soldiers behind them and they're
like for
who dressing the audience a little bit
there Aragorn yeah nobody knows who
froto is they're not supposed to you
shouldn't be yelling his
name dramatic moment though um when
you're building your magic systems
asking yourself what the magic cannot do
or you know splitting up so what are the
costs of the magic your cost of your
magic is going to have a deep influence
on your magic system it can be like Dune
and mistborn an economic cost on one
hand uh it is expensive there's a
material cost you have to do this it can
be have a physical cost it can just be
hard to use you can have an intellectual
cost you have to learn to use it um it
can have other kind of mystical costs
like but those will how big the costs
are will influence how you use the magic
the one I always joke with is like if
you have a magic that's really powerful
but each time you use it one of your
grandparents has to
die you can use that magic as limited
number of times and it's a very
different sort of story than oh no I'm
going to run out of metal um do be aware
that some of the costs you have to be
careful with because um how much metal a
character has or how much strength a
character has is very similar to how
many bullets are in the gun of a
gunslinger and an old
western the reader kind of understands
that they're going to run out of
narrative at narratively appropriate uh
moments you want to be careful not to
show the hand of the author too much by
at least having the character say I'm
almost out I'm running low I can maybe
do a little bit more Let Let the reader
be able to gauge how much that is
usually that's better than adding a
number to it that they have to track but
sometimes having a number like you know
the I have four bullets left can be
really effective okay um I'm going to
get through all this before I go
questions so costs costs are very useful
and help helping limit um but you know
um Flaws by my definition flaws are the
things that the reader is expected to
expect the characters to overcome come
so in a magic system a flaw to a magic
system might be the things that we're
talking about where we highlight early
on hey the magic can't do this except
sometimes it can well we're going to
have to figure out and overcome and fix
that flaw in the magic um aess is a
flawed magic system story The Magic used
to work it no longer does we have to
figure out how to make it work
narratively for me a flaw is we you
expect the characters to fix this and
they
um whereas you have limitations on a
magic are just what the magic can and
can't
do you know alaman pushes directly away
from you pulls directly towards you
you're not expecting the reader the
characters to figure out a way around
that or to you know to to fix that that
just exists and they're going to use
that and have to manipulate it and uh
it's part of the magic system and then
there's the sort of hindrances thing
uh which for magic systems is a little
bit different um I always think of the
hindrances of the you know the lines
that you don't want to cross but that
you could if you really wanted to and we
aren't sure if we want the characters to
cross them or not um but these are all
different things that you can add to a
magic system and generally these will be
where your story
lies and where the flaws the limitations
uh the costs are they will not with what
the powers can do what the ring can do
is make saaron super powerful what the
flaws and limitations are are where the
story is it can be destroyed by throwing
it in Mount Doom Argo we're going to try
to make use of that um that flaw in the
one ring that is actually an advantage
to us we're going to fix it we're going
to break the thing okay questions on
flaws being more interesting than Powers
you had one yeah I just was actually
going to make a comment there is a story
called the misenchanted sword that's a
really good example of the cost it's
about a sword that can only be drawn so
many times and once they pass that
threshold it turns and kills the wielder
and finds a new owner yeah is that oh
yeah I've read about I've read that
story was that elre the camp who wrote
that I can't remember it was from my
yeah it's a classic uh we should look
that up uh it's a good story yeah um so
the story was called the misenchanted
sword the misenchanted sword who wrote
it lawence Wat
okay Lawrence wat Evans okay oh yeah I I
know Lawrence um yeah okay I should know
that I know Lawrence sorry Lawrence
um it's a good story uh reminds me of
the uh the saberhagen swords books which
had some interesting things back in the
80s um so yeah uh other comments or
questions we'll go here and then here
differentiate differentiating hindrances
from flaws could something maybe start
as a flaw where you think it needs to be
fixed but then it turns out it's more of
a hindrance yes exactly you can change
these starts as a flaw then you realize
no we want this um the classic example
of this is um a lot of stories you'll
you'll have the story where they realize
if they solve the
flaw something worse happens this is
here for a reason and then they decide
to work around it instead or to keep it
or to not take that extra step uh that
happens a ton uh no I won't give
spoilers but I've done it before and a
very large uh and important uh work that
I worked on so yeah um do you have any
tips on catering your flaw your flaws in
your magic system towards the characters
or oh yeah flaws in the magic system
toward characters um do I have any tips
on doing that I say it's generally a
good idea um this is often where you
pull theme Into Your World building is
by matching the magic system in some way
to your characters um and to the kind of
story at large um and when you start
pulling those things in with your world
building then it you can really build
theme and whatnot like you know Paul at
trates Right comes from a land of water
he then needs to go to Dune where there
is no water except the magical water
that he needs to drink in order to
become uh you know Lis Al um right and
so suddenly the mag like his background
and one of the major sources of the
magic are intertwined in interesting
ways and you start to build theme of
Water of Life blood being water what
will return water to Dune um should we
do this and all of that stuff comes out
of just building into the magic system
these um these limitations these aspects
of it that relate to character um and
this is this is you know this is great
stuff uh you can do this so yes I would
just caution of put too many flaws how
do you like how do you how do you make
sure not to do too many flaws your uh
beta readers will help you with this but
yeah you can over you could basically
this is where sanderson's thirdd law
comes into play you can over complicate
your worlds real fast um and you got to
be careful about this usually a couple
of elegant rules are way more viable
than 30 very interesting but finicky
rules um and that goes for both flaws
and Powers um you know the length of the
series depends on how much you can get
but I'll tell the story um with
sanderson's third law about that in a
minute here so all right all right last
question on this one I talked way too
long on sanderson's first law yeah so
you want flawed characters and also
flaws in Magic systems
would you advise against having a flawed
character with the flawed magic system
is that like Rel to that too many flaws
no uh the question is would you would I
avoid having a flawed character with a
flawed magic system no uh definitely not
every character should have some sort
they don't have to be they don't have to
be flaw flaws they can be any one of the
kind of four things that I'm talking
about but the most interesting
characters have these uh problems the
most interesting magic systems have
these problems um I would say that your
most interesting stories happen at the
intersection of those things um right
like um yeah uh name of the wind is
partially compelling because quo is a
deeply flawed character and he's
searching for a magism that he does not
understand in a world where he's used to
being able to explain the magic using
rules because name of the wind has a
soft and a hard magic and he's really
good at the Hard magic and he wants to
learn the soft magic and it's beyond his
reach because of the way he his mind um
and his desires work but it's like the
mythical Muse that he chases and so he
spends I'm going to guess all three
books but at least two of the books
chasing don't laugh Pat is trying he
really is um he's chasing this thing
that he can't quite have and it's deeply
troubling to him and that's part of what
makes those books work so um all right
we we got a few minutes left so we're
going to do sanderson's third law
uh after Miss Bourne took off and got um
uh started hitting the bestseller list
and War breaker came out people started
asking me what my next uh book series
was going to be and I started telling
them about the way of Kings um this is
in part because for whatever reason
Amazon figured out that I was going to
write a book called The Way of Kings I
can't get in now when they have five
minutes but they put up a listing for it
um and so my fans started saying what's
the way of Kings I'm like oh it's my
giant fantasy epic uh it's going to be
my Magnum open they're like oh and then
they'd be like mbor had three magic
systems how many Magic systems does
Stormlight have and I'd be like
30 uh and I got pulled into this hype of
bigger is
better um and this is really dangerous
because you want to be giving people
more and more and more uh but if uh
movies have taught us super hero movies
T us anything more villains don't make
for better stories right um and indeed
more magism don't necessarily make for
better uh
stories um and what I realized I was
kind of going crazy uh and part of the
reason that uh way of King's Prime had
failed it's because I tried to do 10
character arcs and way of Kings when I
wrote it worked better because I really
focused on a couple of character arcs
and in the same way I focused on a
couple of aspects of the magic uh and I
started using this
rule uh to tell myself to make sure
that instead of adding something new I
explore what I already have uh there's
lots of depth to explore to changing
simple things simple rules uh to physics
change you can write entire books about
small changes and so it doesn't mean you
can't add new things it just means
before you do ask yourself can I do more
with what I have example of this if
you've got a really in um religion in
your books and you're going to be adding
you know another culture with a
different religion often first ask
yourself okay can I take what I have the
religion I have would it be more
interesting if these were two different
branches of the same religion such as
Judaism and Christianity um does that
add to my story and a lot of times the
answer will be oh yeah it adds way more
interesting sort of interconnective
to have these two magic uh these two
religions be cousin religions um because
it adds kind of this different kind of
take on some things that happened and
different Phil uh philosophical takes on
History um with your magic before you
say you know I'm going to add a new
complete magic system say if I really
explored every aspect of my magic system
can I make a character who uses it in a
different way and in a different
interesting way can I explore that
instead what you want to avoid is I
referenced Skyrim
earlier um in the Elder Scroll series
they they tend to be pretty good games
but some of the earlier games had this
problem where like I remember when I
played Daggerfall this is how old I am
okay I played Daggerfall um back when
like it took yeah I I played Daggerfall
and Daggerfall had this uh this thing
where it had like 10,000
dungeons it was my first experience with
procedural generation it was 10,000
dungeons that repeat the same 50 uh
different elements 10,000 different ways
so if you went through one the second
one was already
boring and um early games had this
problem they would say it is an ocean an
inch deep you want to avoid having your
world building be an ocean an inch deep
and instead you want to have a
handcrafted in the newer you know Skyrim
gam is like we put in you know 50
dungeons and make them all really good
we have a better
game save your questions on this I'll
give you a chance to dig into second and
third law questions next week um when we
get then go into more World building
stuff so thank you all very much and
I'll see you next week hopefully I'll be
better by then